<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../tohtml.xsl?root=maemo-mapper"?>

<!-- 
 - 
 - Copyright (C) 2006, 2007 John Costigan. 
 - 
 - This file is part of Maemo Mapper. 
 - 
 - Maemo Mapper is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify 
 - it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by 
 - the Free Software Foundation, either version 3 of the License, or 
 - (at your option) any later version. 
 - 
 - Maemo Mapper is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, 
 - but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of 
 - MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the 
 - GNU General Public License for more details. 
 - 
 - You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License 
 - along with Maemo Mapper.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>. 
 - 
--> 
 
<ossohelpsource>
  <folder>
    <title>Maemo Mapper</title>
    <topic>
      <topictitle>Introduction</topictitle>
      <context contextUID="help_maemomapper_intro"/>
      <para>Welcome to Maemo Mapper.</para>
      <para>
        Maemo Mapper is a geographical mapping tool that can be used to:
      </para>
      <list>
        <listitem>
          Download map data to your device's main memory or to an external
          memory card.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          View that map data on the screen.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Navigate that map data by panning around the screen and zooming in
          and out.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Display your position and other GPS information from a GPS
          receiver.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Store and display Point-of-Interest (POI) data.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Download directions between arbitrary points on the map.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Save or open track data or route data.
        </listitem>
      </list>
      <para>
        Use the <ref refid="help_maemomapper_" refdoc="index"/> to peruse the
        various sections of this help document, or go to <ref
          refid="help_maemomapper_getstarted" refdoc="Getting Started"/> to
        get up and running quickly.
      </para>
    </topic>
    <topic>
      <topictitle>Getting Started</topictitle>
      <context contextUID="help_maemomapper_getstarted"/>
      <para>
        When you first start Maemo Mapper, you will be presented with the
        <display_text>Settings</display_text> dialog box.  Most of the
        settings have reasonable defaults, but if you have a GPS receiver,
        you should fill in the <display_text>Bluetooth</display_text> field
        with the MAC address of your GPS receiver.  If you don't know the
        MAC, turn on your GPS receiver and push the
        <display_text>Search</display_text> button.  Maemo Mapper will
        attempt to automatically discover the MAC address of your receiver.
        For more information about the <display_text>Settings</display_text>
        dialog box, see <ref refid="help_maemomapper_settings"
          refdoc="Settings"/>.
      </para>
      <para>
        Alternatively, you can leave the
        <display_text>Bluetooth</display_text> field blank, and Maemo Mapper
        will attempt to automatically search for and use any bluetooth GPS
        receivers that it can identify.  This is particularly useful if you
        tend to use multiple different GPS receivers.  This feature is not
        guaranteed to work on all Nokia devices or with all bluetooth GPS
        receivers.
      </para>
      <note>
        If you are using Maemo Mapper on a device with an internal GPS
        receiver, then you should probably use the "Bluetooth" receiver type
        and leave the field empty.
      </note>
      <para>
        When you are finished setting up Maemo Mapper to your preferences,
        pressing the <display_text>Ok</display_text> button will lead you to
        another dialog box: the <display_text>Manage
          Repositories</display_text> dialog.
      </para>
      <para>
        To get started quickly, press the
        <display_text>Download...</display_text> button.  Maemo Mapper will
        download a set of pre-defined repository information for you to use.
        If you use the pre-defined repositories, you can delete the
        <display_text>Default</display_text> repository.  For more
        information about repositories and the <display_text>Manage
          Repositories</display_text> dialog, see
        <ref refid="help_maemomapper_repoman"
          refdoc="Managing Repositories"/>.
      </para>
      <para>
        Certain repositories (most notably, the commercial ones) may have
        license agreements attached with their use.  It may be illegal to
        use a certain repository with Maemo Mapper or under certain
        conditions.  This includes the repositories downloaded via the
        <display_text>Download...</display_text> button.  If you are not
        sure if you are legally allowed to use a particular repository, you
        should delete it from your list of repositories.  The authors of
        Maemo Mapper cannot be held responsible for your use of a particular
        repository.
      </para>
      <para>
        Once you have your Repositories set up the way you like, press the
        Ok button, and you will be presented with a blank screen, because
        you have not yet actually downloaded any map data to your device.
        To allow Maemo Mapper to automatically download map data as it
        becomes needed on the display, enable the
        <display_text>Auto-Download</display_text> checkbox in the
        <display_text>Maps</display_text> menu.
      </para>
      <para>
        If you have a working internet connection, Maemo Mapper will attempt
        to download maps and display them on the screen automatically as
        the downloads complete.  You should see a map of the world.  Be
        careful when you enable Auto-Download, because it can quickly fill
        your available disk space.  See
        <ref refid="help_maemomapper_mapman" refdoc="Managing Maps"/> for
        details on how to manage disk space for a particular repository.
      </para>
      <heading>The Graphical User Interface</heading>
      <para>
        The main view of Maemo Mapper emphasizes simplicity.  By default,
        the map is all that is displayed.  You current position (if you have
        a GPS receiver) is indicated by a blue circle.  The blue line
        extending from the blue circle indicates your current heading and
        speed.  <i>Tracks</i> are red and represent where you have been.
        <i>Routes</i> are green and represent where you want to go, i.e.
        directions to a location.
      </para>
      <para>
        The hardware buttons on your device provide quick access to common
        functionality:
      </para>
      <list>
        <listitem>
          <graphic filename="2686KEY_full_screen"/> - Toggle
          Full-Screen Mode
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <graphic filename="2686KEY_zoom_in"/> - Zoom In - hold down to
          zoom multiple levels at a time
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <graphic filename="2686KEY_zoom_out"/> - Zoom Out - hold down to
          zoom multiple levels at a time
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <graphic filename="2686KEY_scroll_up"/> - Pan Up - hold down to
          scroll
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <graphic filename="2686KEY_scroll_down"/> - Pan Down - hold down
          to scroll
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <graphic filename="2686KEY_scroll_left"/> - Pan Left - hold down
          to scroll
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <graphic filename="2686KEY_scroll_right"/> - Pan Right - hold down
          to scroll
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <graphic filename="2686KEY_scroll_center"/> - Toggle Auto-Center
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <graphic filename="2686KEY_esc"/> - Programmable; defaults
          to: Hide/Show Tracks and Routes
        </listitem>
      </list>
      <para>
        You can also pan around the map by tapping on the screen.  Maemo
        Mapper will center the display on where you tapped.  If you had
        <display_text>Auto-Center</display_text> enabled, tapping a location
        to center on it will automatically disable that functionality.
      </para>
      <para>
        From this point, you can use the menus to manage routes, tracks, and
        map data; to change the view; to change settings; or to see detailed
        GPS information (if you have a GPS receiver).
      </para>
      <para>
        There is also a context-sensitive menu that appears on the map when
        you tap and hold a location on the map.  From that menu, you can
        download directions, calculate distances, or add/modify
        Point-of-Interest (POI) data.
      </para>
      <para>
        For help with any of these features, use the
        <ref refid="help_maemomapper_" refdoc="index"/>.
      </para>
    </topic>
    <topic>
      <topictitle>Main Menu</topictitle>
      <context contextUID="help_maemomapper_mainmenu"/>
      <para>
        This help topic describes the functionality of each of the menu
        items in Maemo Mapper.
      </para>
      <heading>Route</heading>
      <para>
        The <display_text>Route</display_text> menu is used to manipulate
        the current <i>route</i>.  A route in Maemo Mapper is defined as a
        set of points and waypoints describing <i>where you would like to
          go</i>, e.g. driving directions from 123 Main Street to 456 Elm
        Street.  It can include multiple segments.  The current route is
        empty until you open or download a route.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <display_text>Route</display_text> menu has the following menu
        items:
      </para>
      <list>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Open...</display_text> - Open a route from a GPX
          file on the file system.  The opened route is <i>appended</i> to
          the current route, so you can string together different routes
          together to create a trip with multiple destinations.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Download...</display_text> - Download a route from
          the internet.  See <ref refid="help_maemomapper_downroute"
            refdoc="Download Route"/> for more information.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Save...</display_text> - Save the current route to a
          GPX file on the file system.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Show Distance to Next Waypoint</display_text> - Show
          the distance left to be traveled (along the current route) until
          the next waypoint.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Show Distance to End of Route</display_text> - Show
          the distance left to be traveled (along the current route) until
          the end of the current route.  The calculated distance includes
          the distance between breaks in the route (i.e. between the end of
          one route segment and the beginning of another route segment).
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Reset</display_text> - Reset Maemo Mapper's tracking
          of your progress along the current route.  Use this if Maemo
          Mapper loses track of where you are with respect to the current
          route.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Reset</display_text> - Clear the current route,
          effectively replacing it with an empty route.
        </listitem>
      </list>
      <heading>Track</heading>
      <para>
        The <display_text>Track</display_text> menu is used to manipulate
        your current <i>track</i>.  A track in Maemo Mapper is defined as
        a set of points along which you have been traveling, i.e.  <i>where
          you have been</i>.  It can include multiple segments.  Tracks are
        most useful if you have enabled a GPS receiver.  The current track
        is empty until you get at least one valid position point from your
        GPS receiver, and it is appendeded to whenever you stray far enough
        from the last track point.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <display_text>Track</display_text> menu has the following menu
        items:
      </para>
      <list>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Open...</display_text> - Open a track from a GPX
          file on the file system.  In contrast to route data, the opened
          track is <i>prepended</i> to the current track, so if you are
          trying to rebuild previous track data, you must open the tracks
          backward in time (most recent tracks first).
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Save...</display_text> - Save the current track to a
          GPX file on the file system.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Insert Break</display_text> - Artificially insert a
          break in your current track data.  This simulates the loss and
          re-acquisition of a GPS fix, and it can be used to track, for
          example, refueling stops.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Insert Mark</display_text> - Artificially insert a
          mark with a description in your current track data.  This can be
          used to mark important landmarks.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Show Distance from Last Break</display_text> - Show
          the distance traveled (along the current track) since the last
          break.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Show Distance from Beginning</display_text> - Show
          the distance traveled (along the current track) since the
          beginning of the track.  The calculated distance includes the
          distance between breaks in the track (i.e. between when a GPS fix
          is lost and later re-acquired).
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Clear</display_text> - Clear the current track,
          effectively replacing it with an empty track.
        </listitem>
      </list>
      <heading>Maps</heading>
      <para>
        The <display_text>Maps</display_text> menu is used to control your
        map repositories.  This menu will be populated with a list of all of
        your map repositories, from which you can select to switch to a
        particular repository.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <display_text>Maps</display_text> menu has the following menu
        items in addition to the list of available repositories:
      </para>
      <list>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Manage Maps...</display_text> - Download or delete
          maps for the currently selected repository.  For more details, see
          <ref refid="help_maemomapper_mapman" refdoc="Managing Maps"/>.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Manage Repositories...</display_text> - Configure
          each of your available repositories, or add new ones.  You can
          also download a pre-defined set of repositories.  For more
          details, see <ref refid="help_maemomapper_repoman"
            refdoc="Managing Repositories"/>.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Auto-Download</display_text> - Toggle Maemo Mapper's
          ability to automatically download maps as they are needed in order
          to fill the screen with map data.  This is useful for arbitrary
          exploration of the world while connected to the internet, or if
          you have a constant connection to the internet (i.e. via a
          cellular data service).
        </listitem>
      </list>
      <heading>View</heading>
      <para>
        The <display_text>View</display_text> menu allows you to customize
        the view by showing or hiding certain features of the display.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <display_text>View</display_text> menu has the following menu
        items:
      </para>
      <list>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Zoom In</display_text> - Zoom in by one zoom level.
          You can also use the <graphic
            filename="2686KEY_zoom_in"/> button.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Zoom Out</display_text> - Zoom out by one zoom
          level.  You can also use the <graphic
            filename="2686KEY_zoom_out"/> button.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Full Screen</display_text> - Toggle full-screen
          mode.  You can also use the <graphic
            filename="2686KEY_full_screen"/> button to toggle
          full-screen mode.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Scale</display_text> - Toggle the display of the
          scale.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Route</display_text> - Toggle the display of routes.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Track</display_text> - Toggle the display of tracks.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Velocity Vector</display_text> - Toggle the display
          of the velocity vector (the blue line extending from the blue
          circle that represents your current location).
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>POIs</display_text> - Toggle the display of POIs.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>POI Categories...</display_text> - Define POI
          categories and which categories are displayed on the map.  For
          more details, see <ref refid="help_maemomapper_poicat" refdoc="POI
            Categories"/>.
        </listitem>
      </list>
      <heading>Auto-Center</heading>
      <para>
        The <display_text>Auto-Center</display_text> menu is used to control
        whether or not Maemo Mapper should re-center the display as your
        current location changes.  The sensitivity of re-centering (how
        close you get to the edge of the display before Maemo Mapper
        re-centers the display) can be configured in the <ref
          refid="help_maemomapper_settings" refdoc="Settings"/> Dialog.
      </para>
      <para>
        There are three different modes of Auto-Center:
      </para>
      <list>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Lat/Lon</display_text> - Keep your location centered
          on the display.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Lead</display_text> - Depending on your speed, keep
          a location in front of you centered on the screen.  The faster you
          are going, the more lead distance is used.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>None</display_text> - Do no re-center the display
          automatically.
        </listitem>
      </list>
      <heading>Go to</heading>
      <para>
        The <display_text>Go to</display_text> menu is used to center the
        view on a particular location.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <display_text>Go to</display_text> menu has the following menu
        items:
      </para>
      <list>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Lat/Lon...</display_text> - Specify an exact
          Latitude and Longitude on which to center the display.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>GPS Position</display_text> - Center the display on
          your current GPS position.  This is the manual counter-part of
          the <display_text>Auto-Center</display_text> functionality
          mentioned above.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Next Waypoint</display_text> - Center the display on
          the next waypoint in your route.  By default, the next waypoint is
          colored a slightly darker green than normal waypoints.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Nearest POI</display_text> - Center the display on
          the enabled POI nearest to the current view center.
        </listitem>
      </list>
      <heading>GPS</heading>
      <para>
        The <display_text>GPS</display_text> menu is used to access features
        of the GPS receiver, including textual information not displayed on
        the map.  It is also used to control your connection to the GPS
        receiver.
      </para>
      <list>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Enable GPS</display_text> - Toggle communication
          with a GPS receiver.  You must have a GPS receiver set up in order
          to use this menu item.  When on, Maemo Mapper will constantly
          search for the GPS receiver.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Show Information</display_text> - Toggle display of
          additional information provided by the GPS receiver.  This
          information will appear in the main display as a panel on the
          left.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Details...</display_text> - Show even more
          information provided by the GPS receiver, including a polar plot
          of all GPS satellites in view.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Reset Bluetooth</display_text> - Attempt to reset
          the bluetooth radio, in case it locks up for some reason.  In
          order for this to succeed, you <i>must</i> add the following line
          to your /etc/sudoers file (if you don't know what that means,
          don't try it): <b>user ALL = NOPASSWD: /usr/sbin/hciconfig hci0
            reset</b>
        </listitem>
      </list>
      <heading>Other</heading>
      <para>
        In addition to the above menus, there are a few other items in the
        main menu:
      </para>
      <list>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Settings...</display_text> - Access and change
          settings for using Maemo Mapper.  For more information, see <ref
            refid="help_maemomapper_settings" refdoc="Settings"/>.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Help...</display_text> - Access this help file.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>About...</display_text> - Display version and
          copyright information.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Close</display_text> - Close Maemo Mapper.
        </listitem>
      </list>
    </topic>
    <topic>
      <topictitle>Context Menu</topictitle>
      <context contextUID="help_maemomapper_cmenu"/>
      <para>
        By tapping and holding on the screen, you can access the context
        menu to execute actions on either that location, the nearest route
        waypoint, or the nearest POI.
      </para>
      <para>
        The context menu is separated into two hierarchical levels.  The
        first level (<display_text>Location</display_text>,
        <display_text>Waypoint</display_text>, or
        <display_text>POI</display_text>) determines what kind of data on
        which the operation applies.
      </para>
      <heading>Location</heading>
      <para>
        The <display_text>Location</display_text> submenu performs actions
        on the exactly latitude and longitude on which the tap-and-hold
        operation was performed.  With that location, you can do the
        following actions:
      </para>
      <list>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Show Lat/Lon</display_text> - Display the latitude
          and longitude of the selected location, in the style chosen in
          <display_text>Settings</display_text>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Copy Lat/Lon</display_text> - Copy the latitude and
          longitude of the selected location to the clipboard, in
          comma-separated decimal format.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Show Distance to</display_text> - Display the
          distance (in a straight line) to the selected location.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Download Route to...</display_text> - Open the
          <ref refid="help_maemomapper_downroute"
            refdoc="Download Route"/> dialog with the selected location
          pre-filled as the destination.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Add Route Point</display_text> - Add a point to the
          current route, based on the selected location.  The point is not a
          waypoint.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Add Waypoint...</display_text> - Add a waypoint
          to the current route, based on the selected location.  You must
          provide a description for the waypoint to be legitimate.  By
          specifying an empty description, however, you can create a break
          in the route.  The break will not be connected to the rest of the
          route, so it can be used to start a new segment.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Add POI...</display_text> - Add a POI to the POI
          database, based on the selected location.  If the category in
          which you place the POI is disabled, it will not be visible on the
          map after creation, but it will still be in the database.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Set as GPS Position</display_text> - Force Maemo
          Mapper to consider the selected location to be the current GPS
          location.  This will not affect the current track, but it will
          change the location of the blue circle that represents your
          current location, and it can be used to calculate a route from
          that location. 
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Apply Map Correction</display_text> - Enables and
	  disables the application of map correction.  When enabling map
	  correction, the tap point is used as the correction reference point.
	  See the note below for more details.
        </listitem>
      </list>
      <note>
        Map Correction is a little-used feature that corrects a rare problem
        with map data.  In some locations around the world (like Brazil and
        Québec), road data from a particular map repository may not be
        accurate, although the error is consistent.  For example, as you
        travel, you may find that your actual track (as indicated by your
        GPS receiver) is a few hundred meters away from the road on which
        Maemo Mapper is drawing your current position.  Map Correction fixes
        this.  When your GPS receiver has an accurate fix, and if Maemo
        Mapper shows your current location as somewhere other than where you
        expect to be, simply tap-and-hold on the location on the map where
        you think your current location <i>should</i> be drawn, then select
        this context menu item.  The correction is saved as part of your
        configuration (so it persists even if you restart Maemo Mapper or
        your device).
      </note>
      <heading>Waypoint</heading>
      <para>
        The <display_text>Waypoint</display_text> submenu performs actions
        on the waypoint nearest to the point on which the tap-and-hold
        operation was performed.  If no waypoints are nearby, an error
        message will be displayed.
      </para>
      <list>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Show Lat/Lon</display_text> - Show the latitude and
          longitude of the selected waypoint, in the style chosen in
          <display_text>Settings</display_text>.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Show Description</display_text> - Show the
          description attached to the select waypoint.  When downloading
          routes via the <ref refid="help_maemomapper_downroute"
            refdoc="Download Route"/> dialog, the description will contain
          the directions needed to take at that waypoint (e.g. "Turn left at
          Main Street.  Go 2.5 kilometers.").
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Copy Lat/Lon</display_text> - Copy the latitude and
          longitude of the selected waypoint to the clipboard, in
          comma-separated decimal format.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Copy Description</display_text> - Copy the
          description of the waypoint to the clipboard.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Show Distance to</display_text> - Show the distance 
          left to be traveled (along the current route) until the selected
          waypoint.  The calculated distance includes the distance between
          breaks in the route (i.e. between the end of one route segment and
          the beginning of another route segment).
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Download Route to...</display_text> - Open the
          <ref refid="help_maemomapper_downroute"
            refdoc="Download Route"/> dialog with the selected waypoint's
          location pre-filled as the destination.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Delete...</display_text> - Delete the selected
          waypoint from the current route.  This will delete all route
          segments surrounding the route, including (and limited to) all the
          points from that waypoint to the next and previous waypoints.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Add POI...</display_text> - Add a POI to the POI
          database, based on the selected waypoint's location.  If the
          category in which you place the POI is disabled, it will not be
          visible on the map after creation, but it will still be in the
          database.
        </listitem>
      </list>
      <heading>POI</heading>
      <para>
        The <display_text>POI</display_text> submenu performs actions
        on the POI nearest to the point on which the tap-and-hold operation
        was performed.  If no POIs are nearby, an error message will be
        displayed.
      </para>
      <list>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>View/Edit</display_text> - View and/or edit the
          selected POI.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Show Distance to</display_text> - Display the
          distance (in a straight line) to the selected POI.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Download Route to...</display_text> - Open the
          <ref refid="help_maemomapper_downroute"
            refdoc="Download Route"/> dialog with the selected POI's
          location pre-filled as the destination.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Add Route Point</display_text> - Add a point to the
          current route, based on the selected POI's location.  The point is
          not a waypoint.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Add Waypoint...</display_text> - Add a waypoint
          to the current route, based on the selected location.  You must
          provide a description for the waypoint to be legitimate.  By
          specifying an empty description, however, you can create a break
          in the route.  The break will not be connected to the rest of the
          route, so it can be used to start a new segment.
        </listitem>
      </list>
    </topic>
    <topic>
      <topictitle>Managing Repositories</topictitle>
      <context contextUID="help_maemomapper_repoman"/>
      <para>
        In Maemo Mapper, map data is divided into specific units called
        <i>repositories</i>.  A repository is a source of map data, each of
        which has its own way of visualizing the Earth.  For example,
        repositories based on street maps typically draw roads as lines and
        buildings as areas, whereas repositories based on satellite data
        draw the Earth as it would appear from space.  There are also
        "hybrid" repositories that overlay street map data on top of
        satellite data, as well as topographical maps that show altitude
        data.
      </para>
      <para>
        Each repository is made up of maps at 16 different zoom levels.
        Zoom Level 0 is the highest resolution (closest to the Earth, i.e.
        "zoomed in"), and Zoom Level 15 is the lowest resolution (furthest
        from the Earth, i.e. "zoomed out").  Not all repositories are
        available at all zoom levels, and some repositories may even produce
        an error (which you can usually ignore) if you try to download maps
        at that zoom level.
      </para>
      <para>
        Once you have set up at least one repository, you can start
        downloading maps from that repository to your device's file system.
        For details on how to do this, see 
        <ref refid="help_maemomapper_mapman" refdoc="Managing Maps"/>.
      </para>
      <para>
        You can set up any number of repositories in Maemo Mapper, but only
        one can be active at any given time.  The <display_text>Manage
          Repositories</display_text> dialog is accessed via the
        <display_text>Manage Repositories...</display_text> menu item of the
        <display_text>Maps</display_text> menu, and it allows you to add,
        edit, and remove repositories.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <display_text>Manage Repositories...</display_text> has a combo
        box that controls which repository is being viewed and edited.  When
        a repository is selected, the controls below it display the current
        settings, which you can change:
      </para>
      <list>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>URL Format</display_text> - A specially formatted
          string that looks like a URL, but it needs to have at least one
          printf-style substitution strings (like %f or %s).  Normally, you
          must either get these URL formats from the internet
          (www.internettablettalk.com is a good source), or you can use the
          <display_text>Download...</display_text> button in the
          Repositories dialog box to download a sample.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Cache DB</display_text> - A database file on the file
          system (either on the device's internal memory, or an external
          memory card) in which maps are stored.  Maps are kept here
          indefinitely (until you delete them), so pick a location with a
          lot of free space.  You can use the
          <display_text>Browse...</display_text> button to select the
          database file with a graphical file system browser, or you can enter
          the filename manually.  The <display_text>Compact...</display_text>
          button can be used to compact the database if you have deleted
          many maps from your database.  (Otherwise, deleted space is reused
          to store new maps.)
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Download Zoom Steps</display_text> - Controls which
          zoom levels should be avoided when automatically downloading maps
          (i.e. Auto-Download is enabled).  The lowest setting (one bar)
          means to download every zoom level.  The highest setting (four
          bars) causes Maemo Mapper to only download every fourth zoom level
          (0, 4, 8, and 16).
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>View Zoom Steps</display_text> - Similar to the
          above-described <display_text>Download Zoom Steps</display_text>
          option, except that it controls how Maemo Mapper behaves when
          zooming.  For example, at two bars, pressing
          <graphic filename="2686KEY_zoom_in"/> causes Maemo Mapper to zoom
          in two levels instead of just one.  Setting this equal to
          <display_text>Download Zoom Steps</display_text> ensures that you
          see all maps at their native resolution.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Double Pixels</display_text> - This forces Maemo
          Mapper to avoid using the native resolution of any maps, instead
          using pixel-doubling.  This is useful if your repository's maps
          contain small, hard-to-read text, and you want to double the size
          of the images to make them more readable.  This setting can also
          affect the zoom levels that are downloaded when Auto-Download is
          enabled.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Next-able</display_text> - This oddly-named option
          determines whether or not the "Select Next Repository" action
          (which can be mapped to any of the hardware keys) will be able to
          select this repository.  When unset, the "Select Next Repository"
          action will simply skip over this repository.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Downloadable Zooms</display_text> - This setting
          governs the minimum and maximum zoom levels Maemo Mapper should
          attempt to automatically download for this repository (when
          Auto-Download is enabled).  Some repositories support more zoom
          levels than others, and supported zoom levels may even vary from
          location to location.
        </listitem>
      </list>
      <para>
        In addition to the per-repository controls, there are a few buttons
        that provide additional functionality:
      </para>
      <list>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Rename...</display_text> - Renames the currently
          selected repository.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Delete...</display_text> - Deletes the currently
          selected repository.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>New...</display_text> - Adds a new repository.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Reset...</display_text> - Resets your repository
          list to the factory default.  This will remove all of your
          repositories and replace them with the single default repository
          that comes with Maemo Mapper.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Download...</display_text> - Downloads information
          about several preset repositories, and adds them to your
          repository list.  They will be appended to any existing
          repositories you already have.  They are not read-only - you may
          edit them as you wish.  This is a good way to get started.
        </listitem>
      </list>
      <note>
        Certain repositories (most notably, the commercial ones) may
        have license agreements attached with their use.  It may be
        illegal to use a certain repository with Maemo Mapper or under
        certain conditions.  This includes the repositories downloaded
        via the <display_text>Download...</display_text> button.  If you
        are not sure if you are legally allowed to use a particular
        repository, you should delete it from your list of repositories.
        The authors of Maemo Mapper cannot be held responsible for your
        use of a particular repository.
      </note>
    </topic>
    <topic>
      <topictitle>Managing Maps</topictitle>
      <context contextUID="help_maemomapper_mapman"/>
      <para>
        In Maemo Mapper, <i>repositories</i> represent sources of map data,
        and <i>maps</i> are just image files (e.g. PNG or JPEG) that are
        drawn onto the screen.  Once you have a repository set up (see 
        <ref refid="help_maemomapper_repoman"
          refdoc="Managing Repositories"/>), you can download maps from a
        repository into a Map Cache, which is just a database file on your
        device's file system.
      </para>
      <para>
        Maemo Mapper downloads maps from the current repository so that they
        can be drawn onto the screen and later recalled from disk, instead
        of downloading a map every time it is needed.  This is called
        <i>caching</i>, and it allows you to use Maemo Mapper even when you
        are not connected to the internet.
      </para>
      <para>
        Because Maemo Mapper downloads maps to your device's file system,
        you must be aware of how much disk space your maps are taking up,
        especially if you enable Auto-Download.  If space is a concern, you
        may also choose to go without a cache entirely.  You can do this by
        leaving the Map Cache DB field blank in the <display_text>Manage
        Repositories</display_text> dialog.  Note that this will cause Maemo
        Mapper to download maps each time they are needed.  If you are using
        a cellular data plan that charges per kilobyte, you probably want to
        use a cache.  For more information about repositories and the
        <display_text>Manage Repositories</display_text> dialog, see
        <ref refid="help_maemomapper_repoman"
          refdoc="Managing Repositories"/>.
      </para>
      <para>
        Aside from the Auto-Download functionality, you can also download
        maps manually using the <display_text>Manage Maps...</display_text>
        menu item of the <display_text>Maps</display_text> menu.  The
        <display_text>Manage Maps</display_text> dialog allows you to
        download, overwrite, or delete maps, either by area or along your
        current route.  It contains up to three tabs, all of which control
        which and how many maps are downloaded.
      </para>
      <heading>Setup</heading>
      <para>
        The <display_text>Setup</display_text> tab controls what you what to
        do.  You can download maps (optionally overwriting
        already-downloaded maps) from the current repository to your
        device's file system, or you can delete maps (pertaining to the
        current repository) from your device's file system.  Both of these
        operations can be done either over a rectangular area or along your
        current route.
      </para>
      <list>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Download Maps</display_text> - If selected, Maemo
          Mapper will download maps from the current repository to your
          device's file system, for the area you specify.  By default, Maemo
          Mapper only downloads the maps that you don't already have.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Overwrite</display_text> - If selected, then Maemo
          Mapper will download maps and overwrite any maps that you may have
          already downloaded.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Delete Maps</display_text> - If selected, Maemo
          Mapper will delete maps from your file system, for the area you
          specify.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>By Area</display_text> - If selected, Maemo Mapper
          will download or delete maps for a particular rectangular area of
          the world, based on the latitude and longitude of an upper-left
          and lower-right corner.  See the <display_text>Area</display_text>
          tab to specify the coordinates.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Along Route</display_text> - If selected, Maemo
          Mapper will download or delete maps along your current route.
          This is useful if, for example, you are about to embark on a trip
          and want to make sure that you have maps for all points along the
          route.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Radius (tiles)</display_text> - If
          <display_text>Along Route</display_text> is selected, then you can
          specify the radius around your route for which maps will be
          downloaded or deleted.  For example, if you specify 4 (the
          default), then Maemo Mapper will download all tiles that are
          within 4 tiles of your route.
        </listitem>
      </list>
      <heading>Zoom</heading>
      <para>
        The <display_text>Zoom</display_text> tab controls which zoom levels
        at which maps are downloaded or deleted.  The current zoom level is
        selected by default, but you can enable or disable any zoom levels
        that you like.
      </para>
      <heading>Area</heading>
      <para>
        The <display_text>Area</display_text> tab, available if the
        <display_text>By Area</display_text> option is selected in the
        <display_text>Setup</display_text> tab, defines the rectangular area
        of the world for which maps will be downloaded or deleted.  If
        applicable, the fields are pre-filled with your current and previous
        view center coordinates.  This allows you to graphically choose your
        rectangle by first centering on one corner of the rectangle, then
        centering on the opposite corner, by tapping the screen or by using
        the <display_text>Lat/Lon</display_text> menu item of the
        <display_text>Go to</display_text> menu.
      </para>
    </topic>
    <topic>
      <topictitle>Downloading Routes</topictitle>
      <context contextUID="help_maemomapper_downroute"/>
      <para>
        Route data can be loaded from GPX files, like the ones provided by
        the GPX Driving Directions web service
        (http://www.gnuite.com/cgi-bin/gpx.cgi).  Or, route data can be
        downloaded directly within Maemo Mapper using the
        <display_text>Download Route</display_text> dialog.
      </para>
      <para>
        Downloading routes requires an active connection to the internet,
        but once a route is loaded into Maemo Mapper, the internet
        connection is no longer needed (unless
        <display_text>Auto-Update</display_text> is enabled).  The route
        download functionality in Maemo Mapper actually uses the
        aforementioned GPX Driving Directions web service.
      </para>
      <para>
        To download a route, you must specify an
        <display_text>Origin</display_text> and a
        <display_text>Destination</display_text>.  The GPX Driving
        Directions web service will return a route taking you from the
        origin to the destination.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <display_text>Download Route</display_text> dialog contains the
        following controls:
      </para>
      <list>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Source URL</display_text> - The web service from
          which driving directions are retrieved.  The default is fine, and
          it is usually left unchanged.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Auto-Update</display_text> - This option, only
          available if <display_text>Use GPS Location</display_text> is
          enabled, will cause Maemo Mapper to automatically re-download a
          new route if you stray from the route.  Note that you must have a
          continuous connection to the internet (i.e. cellular data service)
          for Auto-Update to work.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Use GPS Location</display_text> - If selected, then
          the current GPS location will be used as the
          <display_text>Origin</display_text>.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Use End of Route</display_text> - If selected, then
          the end of the route will be used as the
          <display_text>Origin</display_text>.  This is useful for stringing
          together multiple route downloads into a single route.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Origin</display_text> - If selected, then you must
          enter your own origin.  An origin can be specified in any format
          understood by Google Maps.  Some examples: "25, -43" (lat/lon),
          "68712" (zip code), "San Francisco, CA", "123 Main St, 45112",
          "5th and Main, 12151".  In fact, if your route download fails with
          a "Could not generate directions" error message, you can use
          Google Maps to test your origin for accuracy.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Destination</display_text> - The destination to
          which the directions will lead.  Like the
          <display_text>Origin</display_text>, a destination can be
          specified in any format understood by Google Maps.
        </listitem>
      </list>
    </topic>
    <topic>
      <topictitle>Downloading POIs</topictitle>
      <context contextUID="help_maemomapper_downpoi"/>
      <para>
        Points of Interest (POIs) can be loaded from GPX files, like the
        ones provided by the GPX POI Search web service
        (http://www.gnuite.com/cgi-bin/poi.cgi).  Or, POI data can be
        downloaded directly within Maemo Mapper using the
        <display_text>Download POIs</display_text> dialog.
      </para>
      <para>
        Downloading POIs requires an active connection to the internet,
        but once a POI is loaded into Maemo Mapper, the POI is accessible in
        Maemo Mapper regardless of whether or not you are connected to the
        internet.  The POI download functionality in Maemo Mapper actually
        uses the aforementioned GPX POI Search web service.
      </para>
      <para>
        To search for POIs, you enter an <display_text>Origin</display_text>
        and a <display_text>Query</display_text>.  The GPX POI Search web
        service will return up to 10 matching POIs in the vicinity of the
        origin.  You can access more POIs from the same query by using the
        <display_text>Page</display_text> modifier.
      </para>
      <para>
        Once you have downloaded POIs, they are automatically added to your
        POI database, and you are presented with the <display_text>POI
          List</display_text> dialog to to review the POIs that were
        downloaded and added to your database.  You must manually remove any
        POIs that you don't want in your database.  For more information
        about the <display_text>POI List</display_text> dialog and
        deleting POIs, see <ref refid="help_maemomapper_poilist"
          refdoc="POI List"/>.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <display_text>Download POIs</display_text> dialog contains the
        following controls:
      </para>
      <list>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Source URL</display_text> - The web service from
          which POIs are retrieved.  The default is fine, and it is usually
          left unchanged.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Use GPS Location</display_text> - If selected, then
          the current GPS location will be used as the
          <display_text>Origin</display_text>.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Use End of Route</display_text> - If selected, then
          the end of the route will be used as the
          <display_text>Origin</display_text>.  This is useful for searching
          for points of interests (like hotels or restaurants) near your
          current destination.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Origin</display_text> - If selected, then you must
          enter your own origin.  An origin can be specified in any format
          understood by Google Maps.  Some examples: "25, -43" (lat/lon),
          "68712" (zip code), "San Francisco, CA", "123 Main St, 45112",
          "5th and Main, 12151".  In fact, if your route download fails with
          a "Could not generate directions" error message, you can use
          Google Maps to test your origin for accuracy.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Category</display_text> - Specifies the default
          category in which all resulting POIs will be placed.  You can
          always change the category later.  If you have not yet entered a
          <display_text>Query</display_text> when you select a category,
          then the name of the category will be entered into the
          <display_text>Query</display_text> field for you.  This allows you
          to, for example, quickly search for restaurants and put them in
          the Restaurant category.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Page</display_text> - Specifies the page of results
          that you want to retrieve.  Think of it as the page number in a
          web search.  Page 1 contains the first 10 results.  Page 2
          contains results 10-19.  And so on.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Query</display_text> - A free-form text query that
          describes the POIs for which you are searching.  This can be
          anything from "food" to "hairstylist" to "museum."  Note that the
          selected <display_text>Category</display_text> is not part of the
          query unless you explicitly include it in the
          <display_text>Query</display_text> field.
        </listitem>
      </list>
    </topic>
    <topic>
      <topictitle>Browsing POIs</topictitle>
      <context contextUID="help_maemomapper_browsepoi"/>
      <para>
        Once you have imported or downloaded POIs into your POI database,
        you can use the <display_text>Browse POIs</display_text> dialog to
        search for certain POIs in your database and to view those POIs in a
        tabular format.
      </para>
      <para>
        To browse for POIs, you enter an <display_text>Origin</display_text>
        and a optional <display_text>Query</display_text>.  Maemo Mapper
        will search the database for all POIs matching your query, and it
        will calculate the distance from each POI to your specified
        <display_text>Origin</display_text>.  You may also filter your
        results by <display_text>Category</display_text>.
      </para>
      <para>
        Once your search is performed, you are taken to the
        <display_text>POI List</display_text> dialog, where you can view,
        edit, and delete any of the POIs that matched your query.  For more
        information about the <display_text>POI List</display_text> dialog
        and editing POIs, see <ref refid="help_maemomapper_poilist"
          refdoc="POI List"/>.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <display_text>Browse POIs</display_text> dialog contains the
        following controls:
      </para>
      <list>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Use GPS Location</display_text> - If selected, then
          the current GPS location will be used as the
          <display_text>Origin</display_text>.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Use End of Route</display_text> - If selected, then
          the end of the route will be used as the
          <display_text>Origin</display_text>.  This is useful for searching
          for points of interests (like hotels or restaurants) near your
          current destination.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Origin</display_text> - If selected, then you must
          enter your own origin.  An origin can be specified in any format
          understood by Google Maps.  Some examples: "25, -43" (lat/lon),
          "68712" (zip code), "San Francisco, CA", "123 Main St, 45112",
          "5th and Main, 12151".  In fact, if your route download fails with
          a "Could not generate directions" error message, you can use
          Google Maps to test your origin for accuracy.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Category</display_text> - Filters the results based
          on the selected category.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Query</display_text> - An optional substring which
          must appear in either the label or description of a POI in order
          for the POI to match.  Any spaces, commas, or other punctiation in
          the query must also be in the label or description.  If left
          blank, then all POIs are matched.
        </listitem>
      </list>
    </topic>
    <topic>
      <topictitle>POI List</topictitle>
      <context contextUID="help_maemomapper_poilist"/>
      <para>
        The <display_text>POI List</display_text> dialog is a tabular
        display of POIs.  With this dialog, you can go to a specific POI,
        edit POIs, change the categories of a set of POIs, delete POIs, and
        export POIs to the GPX file format.
      </para>
      <para>
        The main view of the <display_text>POI List</display_text> dialog is
        a table with five columns, all of which (except the checkbox) can be
        sorted by tapping on the appropriate header:
      </para>
      <list>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>*</display_text> - This checkbox column contains a
          checkbox for each POI in the table.  All of the POIs that are
          checked will be affected by operations in the
          <display_text>Checked POI Actions</display_text> dialog, described
          later.  You can tap on the column header to enable or disable
          all of the checkboxes at once.  Note that this checkbox has no
          effect on whether or not the POI is visible in the map.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Category</display_text> - The category in which the
          POI belongs.  Categories can be edited, enabled, and disabled with
          the <display_text>POI Categories</display_text> dialog.  For more
          information about the <display_text>POI Categories</display_text>
          dialog, see <ref refid="help_maemomapper_poicat"
            refdoc="POI Categories"/>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Dist.</display_text> - The distance from the Origin
          to the given POI.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Bear.</display_text> - The bearing (in degrees from
          true north) from the Origin to the given POI.  A bearing of zero
          or 360 means that the POI is due north of the Origin.  90 means
          east; 180 means south; and 270 means west.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Label</display_text> - The label of the POI.
        </listitem>
      </list>
      <para>
        Below the table are four buttons:
      </para>
      <list>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Go to</display_text> - Pans the map display to the
          currently selected POI (i.e. the currently highlighted row).
          Remember that you can tap and hold on the title bar of the dialog
          in order to see the map behind it.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Edit...</display_text> - Opens the
          <display_text>Edit POI</display_text> dialog for the currently
          selected POI (i.e. the currently highlighted row).  You can also
          double-tap on a row in the table to open this dialog.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Checked POI Actions...</display_text> - Opens the
          <display_text>Checked POI Actions</display_text> dialog, which
          allows you to perform actions on the currently checked POIs in the
          table.  From that dialog, you can set the categories of the
          checked POIs, delete the checked POIs, and/or export the checked
          POIs to a GPX file.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Close</display_text> - Closes the <display_text>POI
            List</display_text> dialog.
        </listitem>
      </list>
    </topic>
    <topic>
      <topictitle>POI Categories</topictitle>
      <context contextUID="help_maemomapper_poicat"/>
      <para>
        POI Categories are a means by which you can organize your POIs for
        selective display.  The <display_text>POI Categories</display_text>
        dialog is accessed from the <display_text>View</display_text> menu
        and allows you to enable/disable, add, edit, or delete categories.
      </para>
      <para>
        Each row in the table represents a category.  There are three
        columns displayed for each category:
      </para>
      <list>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Enabled</display_text> - Controls whether or not
          POIs in this category are drawn on the map.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Label</display_text> - A short label to describe the
          category.  This is the name that will be visible when viewing a
          POI.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Description</display_text> - A longer description of
          the category.  This description is not visible anywhere except in
          this dialog; it is only used to get an idea of how the category is
          meant to be used.
        </listitem>
      </list>
      <para>
        Selecting a row in the table and pressing the
        <display_text>Edit</display_text> button will allow you to edit the
        above three attributes of a category, and to delete a category.  You
        can also add a new category by using the
        <display_text>Add</display_text> button.
      </para>
      <note>
        A POI may only be associated with a single category at a time.
      </note>
      <heading>POI Icons</heading>
      <para>
        Icons can be customized on a per-POI or per-category basis, and/or
        you may provide a custom default icon for all POIs.  To do so, you
        should place icon files in the same directory as the POI database
        itself.  Most image file formats are supported, but the files
        themselves <i>must</i> have the ".jpg" extension (even if the icons
        are not in the JPEG format).
      </para>
      <para>
        To customize the default POI icon (to be used instead of the simple
        square), place an icon file called "poi.jpg" in the same directory
        as the POI database.
      </para>
      <para>
        To customize the icon for a POI category, place an icon file with
        the same name as the POI category, all lower-case, plus the ".jpg"
        extension.  For example, if your POI category is called "Gas
        Stations", the file should have the name "gas stations.jpg".
      </para>
      <para>
        To customize the icon for a specific POI, place an icon file with
        a name equal to the POI's label, all lower-case, plus the ".jpg"
        extension.  For example, if your POI's label is "Joe's House",
        the file should have the name "joe's house.jpg".
      </para>
      <para>
        POI-specific icons are given priority over category-specific icons,
        which in turn are given priority over the default POI icon.
      </para>
    </topic>
    <topic>
      <topictitle>Settings</topictitle>
      <context contextUID="help_maemomapper_settings"/>
      <para>
        The <display_text>Settings</display_text> dialog (accessible from
        the main menu) provides access to a plethora of configurable options
        that control how Maemo Mapper appears and runs.  In addition to the
        tabs, which are described below, there are also two buttons at the
        bottom of the diagram labeled <display_text>Hardware
          Keys...</display_text> and <display_text>Colors...</display_text>.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <display_text>Hardware Keys...</display_text> button brings up
        another dialog box, which allows you to customize the actions that
        each hardware key causes.  For example, you can map the 
        <graphic filename="2686KEY_esc"/> button to cycle through map
        repositories, giving you quick access to switching among them.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <display_text>Colors...</display_text> button allows you to
        customize the colors that are used for drawing on-map objects.
      </para>
      <heading>GPS</heading>
      <para>
        The <display_text>GPS</display_text> tab tells Maemo Mapper the
        source (if any) from which to retrieve GPS data.  It is only
        applicable if you have access to a GPS source, such as a bluetooth
        GPS receiver or a GPSD server.  Technically, Maemo Mapper uses GPSD
        for all of its GPS receiver communication, but you can instruct
        Maemo Mapper to use GPSD in one of three ways:
      </para>
      <list>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Bluetooth</display_text> - Select this option
          if you are using a bluetooth GPS receiver, and enter the
          MAC address in the field provided.  If you don't know the MAC
          address, turn on your receiver and press the
          <display_text>Scan...</display_text> button to select it from a
          list of nearby bluetooth devices.  Or, leave the field blank and
          Maemo Mapper will automatically try to use any bluetooth GPS
          receivers that it can identify.  This
          option is also appropriate if you are running Maemo Mapper on a
          device with an internal GPS receiver, in which case you should
          leave the field blank.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>File Path</display_text> - Select this option to use
          a device file on your file system, such as an RFCOMM device, and
          specify the pathname of the file in the appropriate field.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>GPSD Host</display_text> - Select this option if you
          want to connect Maemo Mapper to any GPSD server (local or remote).
          Enter the hostname and port of the server in the fields provided.
          The default values (127.0.0.1 on port 2947) cause Maemo Mapper to
          use the local GPSD server, if available.
        </listitem>
      </list>
      <heading>Auto-Center</heading>
      <para>
        The <display_text>Auto-Center</display_text> tab allows you to
        configure how Maemo Mapper automatically re-centers the display when
        either <display_text>Lat/Lon</display_text> or
        <display_text>Lead</display_text> is enabled from the
        <display_text>Auto-Center</display_text> menu.  The Auto-Center
        feature is most useful in conjunction with a GPS receiver.
      </para>
      <list>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Lead Amount</display_text> - When Auto-Center is set
          to <display_text>Lead</display_text>, then Maemo Mapper will keep
          the center of the screen focused on an area in front of you.  When
          driving, this allows you to view more of the road ahead of you.
          The distance in front of you on which the screen is centered is
          based on two variables: your current speed and the value of the
          <display_text>Lead Amount</display_text> option.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Fixed</display_text> - Controls whether or not your
          lead amount is affected by your speed.  If checked, then your
          speed will not affect the lead amount.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Pan Sensitivity</display_text> - Controls how often
          Maemo Mapper re-centers the display, based on how close your
          position (or the position of your <i>lead</i>) gets to the edge of
          the screen.  When set to a low value, Maemo Mapper will only
          re-center the screen when you are near the edge of the screen.
          When set to the maximum, Maemo Mapper will keep your position as
          close to the center as possible.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Min. Speed</display_text> - Controls how fast you
          must be moving in order for Auto-Center (and Auto-Rotate) to
          activate.  For example, walkers may wish to set this threshold
          low, while drivers with inaccurate GPS receivers may wish to set
          this high (to avoid spurious auto-rotates when parked or waiting
          at a red light).  The speed is specified in your chosen units.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Rotate Sensit.</display_text> - Controls how often
          Maemo Mapper rotates the display based on your heading, depending
          on how far your current rotation is from your heading rotation.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Points</display_text> - Controls which direction
          on the screen your heading points to when auto-rotating.  The
          default is for your current heading to point up.
        </listitem>
      </list>
      <heading>Announce</heading>
      <para>
        The <display_text>Announce</display_text> tab controls how and when
        Maemo Mapper displays or speaks waypoint information.  When you
        approach a waypoint in your route (defined by the presence of a
        description in the GPX file), Maemo Mapper will pop up a text box
        with the contents of that description.  When downloading routes from
        within Maemo Mapper, the text describes your next action, e.g. "Turn
        left at Main Street.  Go 2.4 miles."
      </para>
      <para>
        As you approach a waypoint, Maemo Mapper will continue to display
        the description of that waypoint, so long as you are within the
        range defined by the <display_text>Advance Notice</display_text>
        option, or until you pass the waypoint.  Because the amount of
        notice is dependent on your speed, it is possible to see the text,
        then slow down to a point where the notice disappears.  This is
        possible, for example, if you are stopped at a red light.  The text
        will reappear when you have picked up enough speed to again break
        the <display_text>Advance Notice</display_text> range.
      </para>
      <para>
        If you have installed <i>flite</i>, which is available in the same
        repository from which you downloaded Maemo Mapper, then Maemo Mapper
        can optionally also speak the same directions that appear on screen.
        Maemo Mapper will only speak the directions once, at the exact
        moment you first reach the distance from the waypoint defined by the
        <display_text>Advance Notice</display_text> option.  The same
        directions are on-screen if you need to reference them.
      </para>
      <list>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Advance Notice</display_text> - Controls how much in
          advance Maemo Mapper begins to provide the waypoint description.
          The exact distance at which Maemo Mapper begins to announce a
          waypoint also depends on your speed, so the value of this option
          can be thought of more accurately in units of time.  At the
          minimum value, Maemo Mapper gives you almost no notice.  At the
          maximum value, Maemo Mapper gives you about two minutes of notice.
          Experiment to find your happy medium.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Enable Voice Synthesis</display_text> - If you have
          installed <i>flite</i>, this option will cause Maemo Mapper to
          speak the description of the next waypoint when you enter the
          range defined by the <display_text>Advance Notice</display_text>
          option.
        </listitem>
      </list>
      <heading>Misc.</heading>
      <para>
        The <display_text>Misc.</display_text> and <display_text>Misc.
          2</display_text> tabs contain miscellaneous options.
      </para>
      <list>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Line Width</display_text> - Controls the thickness
          of all lines drawn on top of the map images.  This includes your
          mark, all tracks and routes, and the default POI image.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Unblank Screen</display_text> - Controls when Maemo
          Mapper keeps the display on without user input.  When set to
          <display_text>When Receiving Any GPS Data</display_text>, Maemo
          Mapper will keep the screen on whenever a GPS receiver is
          connected and producing data.  When set to
          <display_text>Never</display_text>, Maemo Mapper will not attempt
          to keep the screen on, and the screen will go blank after a period
          of inactivity on the user's part.  The default is
          <display_text>When Moving (Full Screen Only)</display_text>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Info Font Size</display_text> - Controls the font
          size for all information that is popped up to the user in the
          upper-right corner, including waypoint descriptions.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Units</display_text> - Controls the units in which
          distances and speeds are displayed in the user interface.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Degrees Format</display_text> - Controls how
          latitude and longitudes are displayed in the user interface.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Auto-Download Pre-cache</display_text> - Controls
          how much of the world surrounding the view Maemo Mapper should
          download when <display_text>Auto-Download</display_text> is
          enabled.  When set to the minimum, Maemo Mapper will only download
          the maps that are required to draw the screen.  As you pan around
          the world, you will see black areas where Maemo Mapper has not yet
          downloaded maps, until those maps are downloaded.  If you increase
          the Pre-cache amount, the Maemo Mapper will download more of the
          surrounding areas, making it less likely that you ever actually
          see black areas.  A general rule of thumb is to limit the
          Pre-cache based on the bandwidth of your internet connection, but
          the default setting (two bars) is usually sufficient for most
          people's needs.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Speed Limit</display_text> - Enables notification
          when you have exceeded the given speed limit (specified in the
          units defined via the <display_text>Units</display_text> option).
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Location</display_text> - Controls the location on
          the screen of the speed warning.
        </listitem>
      </list>
      <heading>POI</heading>
      <para>
        The <display_text>POI</display_text> tab allows you to define your
        POI database and how POIs are drawn on the screen.
      </para>
      <list>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>POI database</display_text> - The location on the
          file system where the POI database is located.  The database must
          be in sqlite3 format.  A default (empty) POI database is
          automatically created for you when you first run Maemo Mapper.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <display_text>Show POI below zoom</display_text> - Defines the
          maximum zoom (furthest away from the Earth) at which POIs will be
          drawn.  When zoomed out beyond this level, no POIs will be drawn.
        </listitem>
      </list>
    </topic>
    <topic>
      <topictitle>About Maemo Mapper</topictitle>
      <context contextUID="help_maemomapper_about"/>
      <para>
        Current Version: 2.4.1
      </para>
      <para>
        Maemo Mapper was created and developed by John Costigan (aka
        <display_text>gnuite</display_text>).
      </para>
      <para>
        Copyright © 2006-2007 John Costigan.
      </para>
      <para>
        POI and GPS-Info code originally written by Cezary Jackiewicz.
      </para>
      <para>
        Default map data provided by http://www.openstreetmap.org/ - other
        map repositories are subject to their own licenses and may or may not
        be suitable for use with Maemo Mapper.  It may be illegal to use a
        certain repository with Maemo Mapper or under certain conditions.  This
        includes the repositories downloadable directly in Maemo Mapper.  If
        you are not sure if you are legally allowed to use a particular
        repository, you should delete it from your list of repositories.  The
        authors of Maemo Mapper cannot be held responsible for your use of a
        particular repository.
      </para>
      <para>
        Maemo Mapper is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify it
        under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
        Free Software Foundation, either version 3 of the License, or (at your
        option) any later version.
      </para>
      <para>
        Maemo Mapper is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
        WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
        MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
        General Public License for more details.
      </para>
    </topic>
  </folder>
</ossohelpsource>
